<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>union with God &#8211; Dillon&#039;s Tips</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/union-with-god/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 21:26:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/cropped-512_x_512_logo_for_my_philosophy_and_religious_page_dillonstips_com_make_it_colorful-min-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>union with God &#8211; Dillon&#039;s Tips</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The Dark Night of the Soul: Christian Mysticism and the Path to Enlightenment</title>
		<link>/dark-night-of-the-soul-christian-mysticism-and-enlightenment/</link>
					<comments>/dark-night-of-the-soul-christian-mysticism-and-enlightenment/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dillon Stengel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 15:56:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Anthroposophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophical Insights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ego dissolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[emptiness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mystical path]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mystical traditions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spiritual journey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[union with God]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1494</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Throughout the history of mysticism, the metaphor of darkness has often been used to describe periods of deep spiritual trial. One of the most profound expressions of this concept is found in the writings of St. John of the Cross, a 16th-century Spanish mystic, who coined the term &#8220;Dark Night of the Soul.&#8221; This concept &#8230;<p class="read-more"> <a class=" thunk-readmore button " href="/dark-night-of-the-soul-christian-mysticism-and-enlightenment/"> <span class="screen-reader-text">The Dark Night of the Soul: Christian Mysticism and the Path to Enlightenment</span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Throughout the history of mysticism, the metaphor of darkness has often been used to describe periods of deep spiritual trial. One of the most profound expressions of this concept is found in the writings of St. John of the Cross, a 16th-century Spanish mystic, who coined the term &#8220;Dark Night of the Soul.&#8221; This concept describes a spiritual journey marked by intense inner suffering and the apparent absence of God, yet it is a journey that ultimately leads to deeper union with the Divine. While rooted in Christian mysticism, the experience of spiritual trials akin to the Dark Night finds parallels in other traditions, such as Zen Buddhism and Sufism.</p>



<p>In this article, we will explore St. John’s vision of the Dark Night of the Soul, comparing it to the spiritual crises and transformative moments found in Zen Buddhism and Sufi mysticism. Though each tradition approaches the divine differently, the common theme of spiritual trials leading to enlightenment reveals the universality of the mystical path.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Dark Night of the Soul: St. John of the Cross</h3>



<p>St. John of the Cross&#8217;s <em>Dark Night of the Soul</em> is a description of the soul’s journey through two phases of purification: the &#8220;Dark Night of the Senses&#8221; and the &#8220;Dark Night of the Spirit.&#8221; The first involves detachment from sensory pleasures, while the second entails a profound emptiness and sense of abandonment by God. During this second phase, the soul feels utterly lost, unable to perceive God’s presence, which is experienced as an all-consuming absence.</p>



<p>St. John writes, &#8220;The soul suffers in this state when it finds no consolation in either God or any created thing.&#8221; This profound sense of desolation and longing is considered a necessary process of purification. Through the Dark Night, the soul is cleansed of attachments, illusions, and ego, allowing it to unite with God in the &#8220;luminous darkness&#8221; of mystical experience.</p>



<p>However, this dark and painful journey is not without purpose. The ultimate goal of the Dark Night is spiritual transformation. As St. John explains, &#8220;The more darkness it suffers in its faculties, the more light it gains in the divine.&#8221; In other words, through the emptiness and suffering of the Dark Night, the soul is prepared to experience the fullness of divine love and grace. It is through this spiritual crucible that the soul is purged and made ready for union with God.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Zen Buddhism: Spiritual Trials and Enlightenment</h3>



<p>While Zen Buddhism does not speak of a &#8220;dark night&#8221; in the same way, it has its own version of spiritual trials that resonate with St. John’s concept. One of the most challenging experiences for Zen practitioners is kenshō, a moment of sudden enlightenment. However, before this moment of realization, the practitioner often experiences a period of intense mental struggle and doubt, sometimes described as &#8220;great doubt.&#8221;</p>



<p>The Zen master Hakuin, in his writings, describes how the seeker often feels as though they have come to the edge of an abyss, facing the limits of the mind and self. He famously wrote, &#8220;At the bottom of great doubt lies great awakening. If you doubt fully, you will awaken fully.&#8221; Like the Dark Night of the Soul, this stage in Zen is marked by the experience of emptiness, a loss of ordinary concepts, and the dissolution of the ego.</p>



<p>In Zen, this spiritual trial is seen as a necessary precondition for enlightenment. The practitioner must confront the void, where all attachments and concepts fall away, and only then can the mind experience satori, or sudden awakening. While Zen doesn’t frame this experience as divine union, the process of letting go of the ego and seeing the world &#8220;as it is&#8221; has deep parallels with the Christian mystic’s journey toward God.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Sufism: The Spiritual Trials of Fana and Baqa</h3>



<p>Sufi mysticism also offers a rich tradition of spiritual trials that echo the Dark Night of the Soul. Sufis speak of <em>fana</em>, or the annihilation of the self, as a key step on the path to union with God. Much like St. John’s description of the soul’s purification, <em>fana</em> requires the seeker to let go of the ego, attachments, and worldly distractions in order to be fully absorbed in the Divine.</p>



<p>The Persian Sufi poet Rumi captures this idea in his poetry: &#8220;I died as a mineral and became a plant, / I died as plant and rose to animal, / I died as animal and I was man. / Why should I fear? When was I less by dying?&#8221; This process of death and rebirth in Rumi’s mystical vision mirrors the Dark Night of the Soul’s journey through death to spiritual life. It is a painful process of letting go, of experiencing the &#8220;death&#8221; of one’s individual self, in order to be reborn in God.</p>



<p>After experiencing <em>fana</em>, the Sufi seeker moves into a state of <em>baqa</em>, or subsistence in God. This is akin to the union with God described by Christian mystics, where the soul not only finds peace and rest but is transformed by divine love. In Sufism, <em>baqa</em> represents the enduring presence of God in the life of the mystic, a continuous, living relationship with the Divine after the ego’s dissolution.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Common Threads: Spiritual Crisis and Transformation</h3>



<p>Despite the theological differences between Christianity, Zen Buddhism, and Sufism, a common theme emerges: the necessity of spiritual trials as part of the journey toward enlightenment or divine union. In each tradition, the mystic must confront their own sense of self, experience a deep sense of emptiness or loss, and endure a period of suffering or confusion.</p>



<p>This &#8220;dark night&#8221; is not just a period of suffering for suffering’s sake; it is a means of transformation. As St. John of the Cross says, &#8220;The endurance of darkness is preparation for great light.&#8221; In the same way, the Zen Buddhist’s experience of <em>great doubt</em> leads to <em>great awakening</em>, and the Sufi’s journey through <em>fana</em> leads to eternal life in God.</p>



<p>These spiritual crises ultimately reveal the limitations of the individual self and open the seeker to a higher reality. Whether that reality is described as union with God in Christian mysticism, enlightenment in Zen, or absorption in the Divine in Sufism, the process is remarkably similar. The Dark Night of the Soul, in all its variations across mystical traditions, serves as a profound reminder that spiritual growth often requires us to walk through darkness before we can fully experience the light.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion: Darkness as a Gateway to Light</h3>



<p>The Dark Night of the Soul, as described by St. John of the Cross, remains one of the most powerful metaphors for the spiritual journey. It speaks to the universal experience of spiritual trial—an experience not limited to Christianity but found in many mystical traditions. Whether through the emptiness of Zen, the annihilation of Sufism, or the darkness of Christian mysticism, the path to divine enlightenment often requires one to pass through the shadow of the self.</p>



<p>Yet, as these traditions teach, the darkness is not the end. It is a gateway to the light, a crucible in which the soul is purified and made ready for union with the Divine. Through these trials, seekers learn that the Divine is not something to be grasped through intellect or will, but rather something to be surrendered to with open hearts and spirits, ready for transformation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/dark-night-of-the-soul-christian-mysticism-and-enlightenment/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
