<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>ayahuasca &#8211; Dillon&#039;s Tips</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/ayahuasca/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 21:27:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/cropped-512_x_512_logo_for_my_philosophy_and_religious_page_dillonstips_com_make_it_colorful-min-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>ayahuasca &#8211; Dillon&#039;s Tips</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The Occult, Crowley, and the CIA: How Spiritual Deception and Technology Converged</title>
		<link>/the-occult-crowley-and-the-cia-how-spiritual-deception-and-technology-converged/</link>
					<comments>/the-occult-crowley-and-the-cia-how-spiritual-deception-and-technology-converged/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dillon Stengel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 19:00:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Philosophical Insights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Anthroposophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Aleister Crowley]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ayahuasca]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Charles Manson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CIA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[energy vampirism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Age]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[occultism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spiritual deception]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1064</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The influence of figures like Aleister Crowley and Charles Manson on American culture and spirituality is a complex and controversial topic, often linked to how institutions like the CIA might have covertly shaped the landscape of American belief systems. During the mid-20th century, the emergence of a new spiritual era, often termed &#8220;New Age,&#8221; was &#8230;<p class="read-more"> <a class=" thunk-readmore button " href="/the-occult-crowley-and-the-cia-how-spiritual-deception-and-technology-converged/"> <span class="screen-reader-text">The Occult, Crowley, and the CIA: How Spiritual Deception and Technology Converged</span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The influence of figures like Aleister Crowley and Charles Manson on American culture and spirituality is a complex and controversial topic, often linked to how institutions like the CIA might have covertly shaped the landscape of American belief systems. During the mid-20th century, the emergence of a new spiritual era, often termed &#8220;New Age,&#8221; was seemingly fueled by an orchestrated disruption of traditional religious values and the promotion of alternative, often occult-inspired ideologies. Central to this theory is the idea that the CIA, seeking to weaken the stronghold of Christianity and conventional religious structures, enlisted or allowed figures like Crowley and Manson to become agents of cultural transformation.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Aleister Crowley: The Godfather of Modern Occultism</h3>



<p>Aleister Crowley, known as the self-proclaimed &#8220;Beast&#8221; and a practitioner of dark, occultist rituals, played a significant role in shaping modern spiritual movements. Crowley preached &#8220;Do what thou wilt&#8221; as the ultimate law, a doctrine that encouraged hedonism, personal autonomy, and rebellion against societal norms. While many may see Crowley as an eccentric mystic, some theories suggest his ideas were leveraged by agencies like the CIA to destabilize traditional faith, particularly Christianity, within American society. By promoting figures like Crowley—whether directly or through tacit approval—the agency might have been aiming to create a generation less reliant on religious authority and more open to experimentation with the self, the spirit, and the universe.</p>



<p>Crowley’s connection with entities like Aiwass, whom he claimed to have communicated with during his notorious occult rituals, bears striking resemblances to the modern fascination with shamanic practices like Ayahuasca. Some argue that today’s popularized Ayahuasca retreats, particularly in the West, are a continuation of this occult tradition, syncretizing elements of Crowley’s “Aiwass” with indigenous spirituality. The result is a hybrid practice that takes individuals on deeply personal, often mystical journeys—but these journeys can be deceptive. While participants believe they are connecting with higher consciousness, they may be unknowingly opening themselves up to influences far from divine, as suggested by warnings in scripture.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Manson and the Manipulation of the Counterculture</h3>



<p>Charles Manson, another figure shrouded in mystery and controversy, was a product of this same era. His orchestration of the Manson Family murders in 1969 sent shockwaves through America, symbolizing the dark side of the hippie movement. However, Manson’s influence extended beyond violence; he promoted an anti-establishment, anti-religious worldview, embedded with themes of chaos and racial discord. In many ways, Manson was a harbinger of the New Age movement—though not directly, his rejection of traditional religious morals and glorification of chaos mirrored the spiritual confusion that would follow in subsequent decades.</p>



<p>There are those who believe that Manson&#8217;s rise to prominence wasn’t a natural phenomenon but a carefully engineered one, designed to fracture American society and guide younger generations away from organized religion. The countercultural movements of the 60s, often spearheaded by those deeply involved in occult practices or radical ideologies, marked a shift away from the traditional Christian values that had long been the foundation of American life.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Rise of Energy Vampirism and the Loss of Faith</h3>



<p>Today, the echoes of these cultural revolutions can be heard in the increasing popularity of practices like energy vampirism, which has roots in occult traditions. Many who engage in discussions of energy manipulation or vampirism often believe they are tapping into ancient knowledge. Yet, in doing so, they may be violating their faith in Christ and his teachings of divine protection. Jesus himself taught that those who follow him are part of his flock, and the Good Shepherd protects his sheep. Energy vampirism, by contrast, represents a belief that one must guard against spiritual attacks from other humans, thereby doubting the divine protection God has already promised.</p>



<p>Scripture warns against falling into such traps, urging believers to remember that the thief comes to steal, kill, and destroy (John 10:10). These false ideologies may masquerade as wisdom or self-protection, but they ultimately serve to draw people away from Christ&#8217;s assurance of spiritual safety. By turning to occult practices or energy manipulation, believers risk being deceived by false doctrines that challenge their trust in the Lord.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Christ’s Warning: The Temple Within</h3>



<p>Jesus’ teachings offer a profound counterpoint to the confusion and spiritual wandering promoted by the New Age movement and its forerunners like Crowley and Manson. In the Gospel of Luke (17:21), Jesus reminds us, “The kingdom of God is within you.” He warns against those who claim that the temple is &#8220;this way&#8221; or &#8220;that way,&#8221; for the true temple is not found in physical structures or esoteric practices, but within our hearts. This teaching directly counters the New Age notion that enlightenment comes from external sources or rituals. Instead, Christ calls us to recognize that the source of all spiritual truth resides within, in our relationship with Him.</p>



<p>By grounding ourselves in the knowledge that the temple is within, we can resist the seduction of modern occult movements and the deceptions that accompany them. Just as a scrying orb is used in occult rituals to see beyond the physical world, the modern computer has become a gateway for seeking knowledge, but often at the expense of spiritual discernment. Dr. John C. Lilly, a controversial figure known for his work with altered states of consciousness, once suggested that the computer screen is the perfect medium to communicate with extraterrestrial life or otherworldly beings. While many today see technology as the ultimate tool for accessing hidden truths, the Bible reminds us not to be deceived by those who lead us away from Christ’s teachings.</p>



<p>In an era where technology, occultism, and New Age spirituality have converged, it is more important than ever to discern the true path. Trust in Christ, and recognize that the ultimate truth lies not in the shifting shadows of this world, but in the unwavering promise of the kingdom within.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-occult-crowley-and-the-cia-how-spiritual-deception-and-technology-converged/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
