<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>parables &#8211; Dillon&#039;s Tips</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/parables/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 21:25:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/cropped-512_x_512_logo_for_my_philosophy_and_religious_page_dillonstips_com_make_it_colorful-min-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>parables &#8211; Dillon&#039;s Tips</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Transcending the Curse of the Tree: Salvation Through the Father</title>
		<link>/curse-of-the-tree-salvation-through-the-father/</link>
					<comments>/curse-of-the-tree-salvation-through-the-father/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dillon Stengel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 22:01:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Anthroposophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophical Insights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biblical interpretation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christ]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[curse of the tree]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Father]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[parables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[redemption]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Salvation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spiritual journey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1700</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Christianity hinges on the belief that Jesus Christ’s death on the cross—an instrument of Roman execution and symbol of ultimate suffering—opens the door to salvation for all who believe. Yet, Jesus’ own teachings, at times cryptic and veiled in parables, invite deeper scrutiny of this understanding. In John 9:39, Jesus says, “For judgment I have &#8230;<p class="read-more"> <a class=" thunk-readmore button " href="/curse-of-the-tree-salvation-through-the-father/"> <span class="screen-reader-text">Transcending the Curse of the Tree: Salvation Through the Father</span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Christianity hinges on the belief that Jesus Christ’s death on the cross—an instrument of Roman execution and symbol of ultimate suffering—opens the door to salvation for all who believe. Yet, Jesus’ own teachings, at times cryptic and veiled in parables, invite deeper scrutiny of this understanding. In <em>John 9:39</em>, Jesus says, <em>“For judgment I have come into this world, so that the blind will see and those who see will become blind.”</em> This statement, taken in conjunction with other cryptic sayings of Jesus, suggests that his mission was not simply to offer clarity and salvation but also to obscure truth for some and reveal it for others.</p>



<p>How do these words fit with the notion of salvation? Are they pointing toward a larger divine mystery that transcends the commonly held belief in the necessity of Christ&#8217;s physical suffering? This article will explore an alternative theological perspective: that clinging to the image of Christ’s crucifixion as the sole means of salvation may actually blind believers to a deeper truth—the direct relationship with the Father. By considering Jesus’ own cryptic statements, this interpretation suggests that the way to salvation might involve moving beyond the cursed tree and embracing the Father without reliance on intermediaries.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">The Curse of the Tree: Stagnation, Not Redemption?</h4>



<p><em>Deuteronomy 21:22-23</em> teaches that anyone hung on a tree is cursed by God: <em>“for anyone who is hung on a tree is under God’s curse.”</em> This verse, which Paul references in <em>Galatians 3:13</em>, has long been interpreted by Christians to mean that Jesus took on humanity&#8217;s curse when he died on the cross. However, if Jesus himself is cursed by being hung on the tree, does salvation come from embracing this curse, or are believers called to transcend it?</p>



<p>A provocative interpretation is that the crucifixion, far from being the ultimate pathway to salvation, may symbolize a spiritual distraction. By focusing on Christ&#8217;s suffering, believers risk becoming stuck in a cycle of guilt, sin, and redemption that never leads them closer to the Father. Instead, Jesus’ crucifixion may serve as a reminder that the material world—its suffering and its symbols—must be transcended.</p>



<p>Jesus himself seemed to acknowledge that his teachings would be misunderstood by many. In <em>Matthew 13:13</em>, he says: <em>“This is why I speak to them in parables: ‘Though seeing, they do not see; though hearing, they do not hear or understand.’”</em> His use of parables, often mysterious and difficult to grasp, suggests that his role was not merely to illuminate truth, but also to hide it from those not ready to see it.</p>



<p>In this context, the image of Christ on the cross may be a parable in itself—a symbol that obscures as much as it reveals. Those who cling to this image as the central focus of their faith may be missing the deeper spiritual truth: that salvation is found not in the suffering of the flesh, but in the direct relationship with the Father.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Spiritual Blindness and Judgment: Christ’s Veiled Mission</h4>



<p>In <em>John 9:39</em>, Jesus reveals that his mission was to <em>“give sight to the blind and make those who see blind.”</em> This dual-purpose mission speaks to the paradox of spiritual sight. Those who claim to see—those who think they understand the full meaning of Christ’s life and death—may, in fact, be spiritually blind. Meanwhile, those who recognize their own blindness, their lack of understanding, are the ones who are open to receiving true spiritual sight.</p>



<p>This paradox resonates with another enigmatic statement from Jesus in <em>Luke 23:34</em>: <em>“Father, forgive them, for they do not know what they are doing.”</em> Here, Christ acknowledges the blindness of those who are crucifying him. They do not understand the full weight of their actions, and yet their actions are necessary for the fulfillment of the divine plan.</p>



<p>But what if this statement extends beyond the literal act of crucifixion? What if it speaks to the broader spiritual blindness of those who focus on Christ’s physical suffering rather than the true spiritual message? In clinging to the cross, believers may be repeating the error of those who crucified Jesus—failing to see beyond the material, beyond the suffering, to the true spiritual liberation that comes from the Father.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">The Serpent, the Heel, and the Crucifixion</h4>



<p>Another key passage that adds to this alternative interpretation is found in <em>Genesis 3:15</em>, where God says to the serpent: <em>“He will crush your head, and you will strike his heel.”</em> This verse, often referred to as the &#8220;Protoevangelium&#8221; or the first gospel, is traditionally understood to predict the coming of Christ, who will ultimately defeat Satan but will be bruised in the process.</p>



<p>This imagery of the serpent striking the heel is significant when considering Jesus’ crucifixion. In being crucified, Jesus is “bruised” or injured, but not destroyed. However, this injury is not fatal in the spiritual sense, as Jesus rises from the dead. The physical suffering of the crucifixion, then, may be a temporary &#8220;bruising&#8221; of Christ, but the ultimate victory is spiritual, not physical.</p>



<p>In light of this, the focus on Jesus’ physical death and suffering—the &#8220;bruising of the heel&#8221;—may be misplaced. The real victory lies not in the crucifixion itself, but in the transcendence of that suffering through resurrection. This suggests that salvation is not found in embracing the suffering of Christ, but in moving beyond it, toward the spiritual reality of the Father.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">The Idle Word: Disregarding the Carnal World</h4>



<p>Another key element in this alternative perspective is the concept of the &#8220;idle word.&#8221; In <em>Matthew 12:36</em>, Jesus warns: <em>“But I tell you that everyone will have to give account on the day of judgment for every idle word they have spoken.”</em> If we extend this concept of the &#8220;idle word&#8221; to the crucifixion, could it be that the fixation on Christ’s physical suffering—the “<a href="https://biblehub.com/interlinear/matthew/13.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">idle word</a>” of the material world—distracts from the true, eternal word of the Father?</p>



<p>The carnal world, represented by the suffering of Jesus on the cross, may be nothing more than a temporary, material distraction. As Jesus said in <em>Matthew 6:19-20</em>: <em>“Do not store up for yourselves treasures on earth, where moths and vermin destroy, and where thieves break in and steal. But store up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where moths and vermin do not destroy, and where thieves do not break in and steal.”</em></p>



<p>By clinging to the image of Christ on the cross, believers may be &#8220;storing up treasures on earth&#8221;—focusing on the material suffering and sacrifice of Christ, rather than the spiritual treasures found in direct communion with the Father. The true path to salvation, then, lies not in the crucifixion, but in the rejection of the carnal world and the embrace of the eternal, spiritual reality of the Father.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Moving Beyond the Tree: A Direct Relationship with the Father</h4>



<p>Jesus, in many of his teachings, points toward a direct relationship with the Father, beyond the intermediary of his own physical presence. In <em>John 16:23</em>, he says: <em>“In that day you will no longer ask me anything. Very truly I tell you, my Father will give you whatever you ask in my name.”</em> This suggests that once his mission is complete, the focus should shift from Jesus to the Father.</p>



<p>Jesus’ role, then, is to point believers toward the Father, not to remain the eternal focus of their worship. By clinging to the image of Jesus on the cross, believers may be missing the point: that Christ’s true purpose is to guide them toward a direct, unmediated relationship with the Father.</p>



<p>In <em>John 14:6</em>, Jesus says: <em>“I am the way and the truth and the life. No one comes to the Father except through me.”</em> This statement is often interpreted to mean that belief in Jesus’ sacrifice is necessary for salvation. However, an alternative interpretation is that Jesus is not the destination, but the way—the path that leads to the Father. The focus, then, should not be on Jesus himself, but on the Father to whom Jesus leads.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion: A Call to Abandon the Tree and Seek the Father</h4>



<p>In conclusion, this theological interpretation suggests that salvation is not found in the crucifixion of Christ or in clinging to the cursed tree. Rather, true salvation lies in abandoning the fixation on Christ’s physical suffering and seeking a direct relationship with the Father. By rejecting the carnal world—symbolized by the suffering of the cross—believers can transcend the curse and enter into a living, dynamic relationship with the Father.</p>



<p>Jesus’ own teachings, often veiled in parables, point to this deeper truth: that those who claim to see may be spiritually blind, while those who recognize their blindness can receive true sight. In clinging to the physical image of Christ on the cross, believers may be repeating the mistake of those who crucified him—failing to see the true spiritual message that lies beyond the material.</p>



<p>Ultimately, the call is to move beyond the cross, beyond the cursed tree, and to seek the Father directly. Only then can believers find true spiritual liberation and eternal life.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/curse-of-the-tree-salvation-through-the-father/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
